Okay today's דף daf is מט, mem tes, 49. We pick up
in the middle of מח עמוד ב, mem chet amud beis, נו
nu משנה mishna and we're continuing with topics that relate to the
act of קידושין. kiddushin. And the משנה mishna says as follows: התקדשי
לי בכוס זה של יין ונמצא של דבש. hiskadshi li be-cos ze
shel yayin venimtza shel devash. A man says to a woman marry
me with this goblet of wine and it turns out that it's
filled with honey. של דבש ונמצא של יין shel devash venimtza shel
yayin or honey and it's filled with wine. בדינר זה של כסף
ונמצא של זהב bedinar ze shel kesef venimtza shel zahav with this
דינר dinar of silver and then it's inspected and you see it's
actually gold, maybe it had rusted or something, it looked like silver.
של זהב ונמצא של כסף shel zahav venimtza shel kesef or said
gold and then it was inspected and it was found out that
it was silver. על מנת שאני עשיר ונמצא עני al menas she-ani
ashir venimtza ani on the condition that I am wealthy and turns
out to be poor. עני ונמצא עשיר ani venimtza ashir or poor
and turns out to be wealthy.
Obviously very different. One is saying על מנת al menat
stipulating on the condition that, you know, which makes the whole thing
conditional and that might also be a little more relevant to the
person whether the man is rich or poor, as opposed to whether
the exact object that was given over for the קידושין, kiddushin, אינה
מקודשת. eina mekudeshes.
But in all of those cases because it was different than what
was stipulated, even if you could say you got better,
you got
gold instead of silver or a rich person instead of a poor
person, it doesn't matter. It was different than what was said. Now,
in the case of על מנת al menat that makes sense, you
specifically said on the condition and the condition wasn't met, although there
maybe you could have thought
that even if I'm a poor person or something, or maybe על
מנת al menat is a function of you know what her expectations
are. But anyway, it's more obvious that when you say on the
condition and the condition isn't met. But how about marry me with
this silver coin and it turns out to be a gold coin?
Why should that be a problem? Well that's what רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says. רבי שמעון אומר אם הטעה לשבח מקודשת. Rabbi Shimon omer
im hita'a leshevach mekudeshes. If he deceived her (it doesn't have to
even mean intentionally deceived, it was misrepresented intentionally or otherwise),
but anyway,
it winds up being better than what was said, the קידושין kiddushin
works, whether it's about the money, the object of the קידושין. kiddushin.
So let's take a look and figure these issues in the גמרא.
Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara is going to break it up into
two cases. The first is going to be the object of the
קידושין, kiddushin, and the second is going to be the על מנת.
al menat. All right, so תנו רבנן tana rabbanan our Rabbis taught:
התקדשי לי בכוס זה. hiskadshi li be-cos ze.
So first we're going to figure out
before we get to the debate of the משנה mishna when you
say with this goblet, do you mean the wine in the goblet?
Do you mean the goblet? Do you mean both of them? And
the relevance of this question, well partly it's whether she owns it
or not, and but it's also if it's only going to be
worth a פרוטה pruta if you combine them or if one of
them is worth a פרוטה pruta and the other isn't. So תניא
חדא בו ובמה שבתוכו. tanya chada bo u-ma shebesocho.
One ברייתא braita says that when you say with this goblet, it
means including what's in it, it and what's in it. ותניא אידך
בו ולא מה שבתוכו ve-tanya idach bo velo ma shebesocho another ברייתא
braita says only the goblet and not what's in it. ותניא אידך
במה שבתוכו ולא בו ve-tanya idach be-ma shebesocho velo bo that that
phrase only refers to what's in it and not the goblet itself.
ולא קשיא velo kashya says the גמרא, Gemara, it's not difficult and
they're not actually debating. It just depends on the circumstances. הא במיא
הא בחמרא הא בציירא. ha bemaya ha bechamra ha betziara.
So a major debate in the ראשונים Rishonim which is which. I'll
just tell you the way רש"י Rashi says. If it's the goblet
of water, so who cares about water? Water is irrelevant. So he
says marry me with this goblet of water, you know, it basically
the focus is on the goblet. If it is with wine, so
wine is important, but
but it wouldn't necessarily mean that it's the wine and the goblet.
And רש"י Rashi actually says because people often say here,
have this goblet of wine and you take a drink and you
return the goblet. So when you say a goblet of wine, like
if I say would you care for a glass of Coke and
you say sure and I give you a glass of Coke, you
don't go ahead and walk home with the glass. It's understood that
I mean, you know, would you like a glass of wine? Here's
a glass of wine, you drink the wine you return it. So
glass of wine means I'm giving you the wine and not the
glass. That's that case.
And הא בציירא ha betziara רש"י Rashi says ציירא tziara is a
type of oil or fish brine, and that's something that you store
for a long time. So if I said, oh, would you care
for a jar of my apricot preserves and I gave it to
you, you wouldn't feel that you had to go home scoop out
the preserves and give me back my jar. Although maybe eventually when
you did use the preserves you would ask me if I wanted
my jar back. But in that case, clearly for me to give
you something, you're taking the thing with the jar and taking possession
of it. So it means only the thing with it. Okay, so
those are the three scenarios. All right, now we go on to
the real focus of the משנה. mishna. אם הטעה לשבח הרי זו
מקודשת. im hita'a leshevach harei zo mekudeshes. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says
if it was misrepresented, deceived, but it winds up being better, the
קידושין kiddushin works, whether it's about the money, the object. given or
whether it's about the condition of the person. So we're going to
split that up, we're going to first focus on the question about
the object being given. So the גמרא Gemara says, ולית ליה לרבי
שמעון יין ונמצא חומץ, ve-lait lei le-Rabbi Shimon, yayin ve-nimtza chametz, חומץ
ונמצא יין שניהם יכולים לחזור בהם. chametz ve-nimtza yayin, shneihem yecholim lachzor
bahem. If I go to a store and I say I want
to buy a liter of wine and the guy sells me the
wine and it turns out that it's vinegar, or if I say
I want a liter of vinegar and it turns out that it's
wine, I can, either side can say, hey, that was a mistake,
I want my money back or it was a mistake give me
back my wine, here's the vinegar or vice versa. Now the fact
that it's either side means even though I wound up getting wine
and I paid for vinegar which is half the price, you would
think, well, I don't have a right to say I want my
money back, I got something better out of the deal here. I
mean, the storekeeper can ask for it, but I can't. And the
answer is no, both sides can ask for their money back and
can ask to redo, you know, to reverse the deal because maybe
even though wine is more expensive I'm not interested in wine, I
need vinegar, I got a recipe at home for vinegar. So therefore
in this case, you know, people might even if, you know, honey
might be more expensive than wine, it doesn't matter, you know, I
wanted wine. Now the question of course is this דינר dinar of
silver and דינר dinar of gold because ultimately that's just about value,
right? But תוספות Tosafot says no maybe you're making jewelry, they would
do this, you know, make jewelry with precious metals and with coins
of precious metals. So or maybe I want to melt it down
and make some jewelry out of it. But if it really was
just a question of money, if it was like with this check
for a hundred dollars and it turned out that it was two
hundred dollars on the check or something, that obviously would work, everybody
would agree would work, I'm just giving you more, that's totally לשבח
leshevach or at least רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon certainly would say that
that's fine. Okay, but in this case the גמרא Gemara says nobody
debates this issue of the storekeeper. So even if it winds up
being better, our general assumption is that you ask for something in
particular and it's the wrong thing, so it's not what you asked
for. So therefore, you know, it's a void sale. So even רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon should agree. That's the גמרא's Gemara question. Now of
course you could distinguish and you could say if I'm going to
a store, my primary focus is I want that object and I
might want one type of object not another and it's not a
question about value. But when a woman is getting married, you know,
accepting something for betrothal, presumably she's not doing it because she needs
vinegar for a recipe at home, right? And that's presumably is, you
know, there's like she's not really trading herself for the vinegar. And
she, you know, and she doesn't initiate the whole process because she
wants the vinegar.
So it's a little bit funny that the גמרא Gemara assumes that
the cases are exactly parallel. Nevertheless that's what the גמרא Gemara said,
that if you're if you're talking about an object it might it's
not always about value, difference between, you know, that's what a cynic
is, he knows the cost of everything and the value of nothing,
so it's not always about the cost. And therefore even רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon should agree that it doesn't work because it's not what
was asked for, it was not what was promised. Okay, so how
could it be that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it works if
it's better, if he doesn't disagree with the case of the storekeeper?
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, אלמא, alma, we see איכא
דניחא ליה בחלא ואיכא דניחא ליה בחמרא, ika de-nicha lei be-chala ve-ika
de-nicha lei be-chamra, some people want vinegar, some people want wine. הכא
נמי איכא דניחא ליה בכספא ולא ניחא ליה בדהבא, hacha nami ika
de-nicha lei be-chaspa ve-lo nicha lei be-dahava, some people want silver and
not gold, and איכא דניחא ליה בכספא ולא ניחא ליה
בדהבא. ika de-nicha lei be-chaspa ve-lo nicha lei be-dahava. So why should
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say that it works? Okay, אמר רב שימי
בר אשי, amar Rav Shimi bar Ashi, אשכחתיה לאביי ashkachtei le-Abaye דיתיב
וקמסבר ליה לבריה. de-yasiv ve-ka mesaber lei le-brei.
I found Abaye that was explaining this משנה Mishnah to his son
and this position of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. And he says הכא
במאי עסקינן hacha be-mai askinan כגון דאמר לשלוחו kegon de-amar le-shlucho הבא
לי דינר של כסף haveini dinar shel kesef that the problem is
not
when the woman accepted something and it turned out to be different.
In that case אינה מקודשת. eina mekudeshet. The issue is the woman
knew what she was getting, that's not a question. So from her
end she totally had דעת. da'at. The question is was the man
okay using a more expensive coin and now he's going to have
to pay more? How did that happen? Because we're introducing the idea
that there's a שליח. shaliach. So the man goes ahead and says
to a שליח, shaliach, אמר ליה לשלוחו amar lei le-shlucho הבא לי
דינר של כסף haveini dinar shel kesef ולך וקדש לי את אשה
פלונית, ve-lech ve-kadesh li et isha plonit, go marry off that woman
on my behalf, you know, betrothal on my behalf, and use a
silver dollar of yours to do it and I'll pay you back.
Okay, that's what he said to him. והלך והוליך של זהב, ve-halach
ve-hovil shel zahav, and he went and he married her off with
a golden דינר. dinar. And now the guy's going to have to
pay back for a golden דינר. dinar. So the woman knew what
she was getting, that's not a question, so from her end she
totally had דעת. da'at. The question is was the man okay using
a more expensive coin and now he's going to have to pay
more? So מר סבר קפידא, mar savar kfida, one holds that when
I said silver I meant specifically silver, gold, you know, I don't
want gold, I don't want her to get ideas in her head
or I don't want to have to pay you that much money.
ומר סבר מראה מקום הוא לו, ve-mar savar mareh makom hu lo,
you're just like pointing him in the right direction, you're telling him
you know silver is sufficient, you want to be nicer and give
her even something more and I'll pay you back for that as
well. All right, so that's the question whether that was included in
the husband's intention for the שליחות. shlichus. The חכמים Chachamim say any
change we can't assume he would have been okay with that. And
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says if the שליח shaliach gave the woman
something more we can assume that the husband would be okay with
that. Okay, so גמרא... Gemara... גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says one minute, so
that can't be what's going, I get, I get conceptually that works,
but that can't be the right reading of the משנה mishnah. *Mishnah*.
אי הכי *ee hachi* התקדשי לי *hiskadshi li* התקדשי לו *hiskadshi lo*
מיבעי ליה *mibay lei*. When the משנה mishnah *Mishnah* has the language
'marry me with this silver dinar', it should say 'be married to
him, the guy who sent me'. התעו לשבח leshevach *hit’at’u leshevach*, why
does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, *Rebbi Shimon* say if he deceived her
and it wound up being worth more, התעו לשבח *hit’ahu leshevach* מיבעי
ליה *mibay lei*? It should have said if he, the husband, was
deceived or, you know, if it played out differently than he intended.
מיבעי ליה *mibay lei*. נמצא *nimtza*, and if it says if it
turns out to be gold, מעיקרא נמי דדהב הוה *meikara nami d'zahav
hava*, there was never any misunderstanding. The שליח shaliach. *shaliach* intentionally used
gold instead of silver. So that can't be the right reading of
the משנה mishnah, *Mishnah*. אלא אמר רבא *ela amar Rava*, רבא *Rava*
says okay here, let's try it this way. אני ואריה שבחבורה *ani
v'arya shebachabura*, me and the lion amongst the group, and who is
the אריה שבחבורה *arya shebachabura*?
Excuse me. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, so אני ואריה שבחבורה
*ani v'arya shebachabura*, I and the lion in the group, תרגימנא *targinmini*,
we've explained it. ומאן הוא *u'man hu*, who does that mean, the
lion among us? רבי חייא בר אבין *Rebbi Chiya bar Abbin*. So
here's how the two of us explained it. הכא במאי עסקינן *hacha
bemai askinan*, כגון דאמרה היא Damrah Hi לשלוחה *kigon d'amra hee l'shlucha*.
So she's got to be the one that some misrepresentation happened, that's
clear from the language of the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah*. But we still
want to introduce the idea of the שליח shaliach? *shaliach* to explain
that there's some latitude for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rebbi Shimon*'s position
why a mistake might still work. So she said to her שליח
shaliach, *shaliach*, צאי וקבלי לי קידושין kiddushin מפלוני *tzei v'kabel li kiddushin
miploni*, go and accept קידושין *kiddushin* from that man who's standing over
there שאמר לי התקדשי לי בדינר של כסף *she’amar li hiskadshi li
b'dinar shel kesef*. He wanted me to marry him with a dinar
of silver. So why don't you go there, you know, I told
him I needed to think about it, I decided yes, so do
me a favor, go there to him and accept that money and
accept it on my behalf. והלך ונתן לו דינר dinar של זהב
*v'halach v'nasan lo dinar shel zahav*, and then this שליח shaliach *shaliach*
went and the man gave him, and instead of a silver dinar
gave him a gold dinar.
So now you can explain that it means: he said, you know,
the man still said like marry me with a דינר dinar. של
כסף *dinar shel kesef*, or or maybe it even means the woman
said 'the man who said marry me with a דינר dinar? של
כסף *dinar shel kesef*', and she—it was misrepresented to her, or it
was not what was said was being given, but in the end
it's not that she misunderstood, it's that the שליח shaliach, *shaliach*, you
know, was in the middle. How does that make anything any better?
מר סבר קפידא kfeida ומר סבר Umar savar, מראה מקום mar'eh makom.
היא לו *mar savar kfeida u’mar savar mareh makom hee lo*. Okay,
and one says that she was being מקפיד makpid *makpid*, and the
other says that she was just showing him the direction. ומאי נמצא
דקציר בבבליתא *u'mai nimtza d'katzir b'vavlisa*, and what does it mean that
it was discovered to be gold? דקציר בבבליתא *d'katzir b'vavlisa*, it was
wrapped up in like some type of a wrapping, and when you
undid it you found out that it was actually gold and not
silver. So what does this mean? It means that if it's directly
between the man and the woman, and the man says marry me
with this silver dinar and she says yes, and it turns out
to be a gold one, then the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* wants to
say that even רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, *Rebbi Shimon* would say that's
no good, because for whatever reason she might have had her eye
on a silver dinar and she might have wanted a silver dinar.
Doesn't matter that the gold costs more.
But what happened was she just said 'Hey, that guy said marry
me with a silver dinar, would you go and accept the כסף
קידושין *kesef kiddushin* for me?' And the שליח shaliach, *shaliach* did it,
and it turned out that he wound up in the end giving
him a gold dinar. So in that case,
you know, because somehow because there is a שליח shaliach *shaliach* in
the middle and she's saying the guy who said give a silver
dinar, maybe she's not really, doesn't really care about the silver dinar,
maybe she's really just trying to identify which man it is that
she's talking about. Like if she said the guy wearing the purple
suit said to me 'Go ahead and be married to me' and
the guy, and he went and found out that it was, you
know, the same guy, the right guy, but he was wearing a
different suit, presumably that's immaterial. So maybe when she says 'who said
the silver dinar', that was just a way of מראה מקום mar'eh
makom, *mareh makom*, of indicating who it was that was being talked
about and not indicating that she really cared about the silver dinar.
Now, that all makes sense to some degree, but what's sort of
not clear here is she still was told it was going to
be a silver dinar. So her agreement of yes, even when she
meant to make a שליח shaliach *shaliach*, might be contingent on the
idea that it was a silver dinar. So it's understandable the idea
that when you tell a שליח shaliach *shaliach* go do X, Y,
and Z, there might be some ambiguity as to whether when you
say this, do you mean it has to be exactly that way,
or you trying to just point me in the right direction? So
if I said the man in the purple suit, you're just trying
to point me in the right direction. Said the man who said
me a silver dinar, maybe you're just trying to indicate what man
it is. Okay, and doesn't, but it still doesn't explain why her
דעת *da'as* becomes more flexible, you know, at the end result. Maybe
we should assume that since she had a שליח shaliach *shaliach* do
it, she was empowering the שליח shaliach *shaliach* to make certain decisions.
But anyway, that is the way the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* frames it.
Okay. אמר אביי *amar Abaye*, said אביי *Abaye*. רבן שמעון, רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל ורבי אליעזר Rabban Shimon, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel and Rabbi
Eliezer. כולהו סבירא להו מרא מקום הוא לו. Mareh makom hu lo,
So they all are, and this is really where the גמרא Gemara
was going because it seemed clear when the גמרא Gemara said כפידא
kefida or מרא מקום mareh makom that the גמרא Gemara was borrowing
that language from a known question about how do you make a
שליח. shaliach That’s why we automatically introduced this whole concept of שליחות,
shlichut, that this concept already exists. How precise do we assume you
are when you’re telling certain things to a שליח? shaliach So he
says there are three תנאים tana'im who say that when you tell
things to a שליח, shaliach you know, we can often assume that
you’re just pointing them in the right direction and not being מקפיד
makpid that it has to be exactly that way. Okay, so it’s
רבן שמעון, Rabban Shimon רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
ורבי אליעזר. רבן שמעון הא דאמרין, Rabban Shimon ha d'amrin, רבן שמעון
that we said, that if it turns out being gold, it’s okay
because we should say the woman was just pointing him in that
direction, she really wasn’t מקפיד makpid on the silver per se for
the שליחות. shlichut. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל דתנן, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
ditnan, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel as we taught,
גט פשוט, get pashut, if you have a גט get that is
a simple flat גט, get, okay, עדיו מתוכו, edav mitocho, you sign
the witnesses at the bottom, like a כתובה ketubah and any normal
document, you sign the witnesses at the bottom.
מקושר, mukushar, if it’s a
sewn-up גט, get, they would do this for a כהן kohen that
a כהן kohen shouldn’t divorce his wife in a moment of anger
and then be unable to remarry her because he can’t be married
to a גרושה. gerusha. So they wanted to slow down the process.
So what they said was, when a כהן kohen is coming to
divorce his wife, the way you do it is you write a
document and you leave every other line blank, and then you write
the lines of the גט, get, and then you fold over the
blank on top of the words and you sew it. Then you
fold over the next blank on top of the words and you
sew it, and then the next blank, takes a heck of a
lot of time. And then you have something that looks essentially like
an accordion or a fan, and then you sign the witnesses on
those folds on the back side on those folds. And that slows
out the whole process. Okay, so מקושר עדיו מאחוריו, mukushar edav me'achorav,
the witnesses are on the back.
פשוט שכתבו עדיו מאחוריו, pashut shekatvu edav me'achorav, if you did a
flat גט get and you signed the עדים edim on the back,
ומקושר שכתבו עדיו מתוכו, umukushar shekatvu edav mitocho,
or if you did a מקושר mukushar גט get and the עדים
edim signed on the inside, שניהם פסולים, shneichem psulim, they're both invalid.
רבי חנינא, Rabbi Hanina, any switch is an invalid גט. get. רבי
חנינא בן גמליאל אומר מקושר שכתבו עדיו מתוכו כשר שיכול לעשותו
פשוט. Rabbi Hanina ben Gamliel omer mukushar shekatvu edav mitocho kasher sheyachol
la'asoto pashut. A מקושר mukushar that the עדים edim signed on the
inside is okay because you can not sew, do the sewing, and
then you would have a גט פשוט. get pashut. You would have
a גט get that was all flat. You'd have a lot of
white lines, and somehow that’s not a problem, maybe because סופרים soferim
might leave like double spacing.
So you just don’t fold it and therefore that would be okay.
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר הכל כמנהג המדינה, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
omer hakol keminhag hamedina, it all goes by the practice, by מנהג
המדינה. minhag hamedina. ואבינן בה, V'avinan ba,
now that doesn’t seem relevant to this. What’s מנהג המדינה? minhag hamedina?
We know what the מנהג המדינה minhag hamedina is: that גט get
is on the back and the, I mean, that פשוט pashut is
on the inside and מקושר mukushar is on the back. So the
גמרא Gemara is going to understand that הכל כמנהג המדינה hakol keminhag
hamedina is referring to a different type of a question about when
you told a שליח to do something, what latitude does he have
between these two? ואבינן בה, V'avinan ba, we asked on this, ותנא
קמא לית ליה מנהג המדינה? v'tana kamma leit leh minhag hamedina? Does
the תנא קמא tana kamma not hold of this principle of הכל
כמנהג המדינה? hakol keminhag hamedina? ואמר רב אשי באתרא דנהיגי בפשוטי, V'amar
Rav Ashi be'atra d'nahigi bepashuti, so the cases, again, you have to,
this is a whole discussion in the גמרא Gemara, over in בבא
בתרא, Bava Batra, we’re importing that issue. So the case is you
told a שליח, "Go and write me a גט." get. And he,
you know, or go and write me a גט מקושר, get mukushar,
go ahead and write me a גט פשוט. get pashut. And he
went ahead and he did it, but maybe, but he did something
different from what you asked. So באתרא דנהיגי בפשוט ועבדי ליה מקושר,
be'atra d'nahigi bepashut v'avadei leh mukushar, if the practice in the medina
was to write a simple גט get and he went ahead and
did a גט מקושר, get mukushar, אינמי באתרא דנהיגי במקושר ועבדי ליה
פשוט, inami be'atra d'nahigi bemukushar v'avadei leh pashut, or it was to
do a גט מקושר get mukushar and he did a flat one,
כולי עלמא לא פליגי דודאי כפידא. kulei alma lo pligi devadai kefida.
Everybody would agree that definitely, you know,
he’s מקפיד makpid, because when he said write a גט, get, we
just assume it means write a גט get like the normal way
it’s done. Okay, so everybody agrees that that’s כפידא. kefida. כי פליגי,
Ki pligi, when do they debate? באתרא דנהיגי בין בפשוט בין במקושר,
be'atra d'nahigi bein bepashut bein bemukushar, that both גיטין gittin were prevalent
in that locale. ואמר ליה, V'amar leh, and he said to a
שליח, "עבדי לי פשוט," avdi li pashut, go or, you know, the
סופר sofer or whatever it is, "go make me a גט פשוט,"
get pashut, which is the easier one. ואזל ועבדי ליה מקושר, V'azal
v'avadei leh mukushar, and he went and he made a
מקושר. mukushar. מר סבר כפידא, Mar savar kefida, so one holds that
you’re מקפיד, makpid. that because you switched then it is no good.
ומר סבר, and the one who says רבן שמעון בן גמליאל that
says הכל כמנהג המדינה hakol keminhag hamedina means you kept within the
practices in this locale and therefore since you did a מקושר mukushar
that’s also okay. מרא מקום הוא לו, mareh makom hu lo he’s
just pointing a direction. Now what I failed to mention before is
that the idea of מרא מקום הוא לו is specifically limited to
scenarios where the שליח does something that is more than you asked
for. If it’s less than you asked for, obviously we assume you’re
מקפיד. makpid So when you said silver and he went ahead and
he did gold, he did more than I asked for. Do we
assume when you said silver you meant exactly silver? Or it could
even go ahead and or minimally silver. When he went ahead and
he said here go ahead and just, you know, make me a
פשוט pashut if both are acceptable in the locale, did you mean
it has to be a פשוט pashut or did you mean it's
okay if it's a פשוט? pashut? That suffices. So that's the question
about מקפיד makpid or or מראה מקום. mar'eh makom, When a שליח
does more than is asked but differently than is asked. Okay, Rabbi
Elazar, what's Rabbi Elazar? Elazar, excuse me, דתנן, detnan, we taught in
a משנה. Mishnah האשה שאמרה התקבל לי גיטי ממקום פלוני. Ha'ishah she'amrah
hitkabel li giti mimakom ploni. A woman says to a man, go
ahead and be my שליח or woman to receive my גט get
for me and do it over at the corner of, you know,
72nd and Broadway.
Okay, because you know the guy's going to be there, he said
he'll meet me 72nd and Broadway, so go get my גט get
from him at 72nd and Broadway. וקבלה את גיטה ממקום אחר. Vekiblah
et gitah mimakom acher. And the שליח went and the guy said,
you know, let's first get a Starbucks or whatever, and they went
and got a coffee and then they came out and he gave
it to him at 71st and Broadway.
So
וקבלה את גיטה ממקום אחר, Vekiblah et gitah mimakom acher, פסול, Pasul,
it's invalid. Because she said, no, you're my שליח to accept it
on 72nd and Broadway. ורבי אלעזר מכשיר, Verabbi Elazar machshir, Rabbi Elazar
says it's okay. אלמא קסבר מראה מקום הוא לו. Alma kasavar mar'eh
makom hu lo. So you see that Rabbi Elazar holds that he
was just מראה מקום, mar'eh makom, pointing the way. Now by the
way, it seems very clear that it is this case where the
concept originated, or the language מראה מקום, mar'eh makom. pointing the place,
before it was being used as a metaphor, showing the direction, giving
a general, you know, pointer, general direction. But here literally מראה מקום,
showing the place where he said he would be. And it's also
not a case of harder or easier, it's just a different place.
Okay, so how much do we assume when you're identifying a place
you mean it has to be that place or you're just trying
to make it more convenient? The other cases are a little different,
but by analogy the גמרא Gemara is saying a similar debate when
the שליח goes ahead and does something different but maybe more difficult.
Do we say you were just trying to point it out and
make it easy, or do we say you were מקפיד to do
it exactly that way? And that's what we're claiming is going on
in our משנה Mishnah with רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon when the woman
is saying go and get the guy who said he'd give me
a silver דינר and gives a gold דינר. Was she just trying
to indicate who the guy was, or was she saying it has
to be a silver דינר? And as I said, what's not totally
clear from that is why we assume that, you know, that in
that case when it was different than she expected she'll be okay
with it. But maybe because she's putting the שליח in the middle,
she's stepping back a little from that and we don't assume her
קפידא as much. All right, anyway the גמרא Gemara goes like this.
אמר עולא. Amar Ulla. Now we're going to turn to the second,
the גמרא Gemara without announcing it is now going to turn to
the second part of the משנה, Mishnah על מנת al mnat that
I am a rich and he winds up poor, poor and winds
up being rich. And here the גמרא, Gemara you know, does not
ask the question about wine and vinegar and how could רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon say לשבח is okay. Here it obviously, you know, makes
a lot of sense. It's actually a little ironic because when it's
wine and vinegar according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon the גמרא Gemara
says, oh no, no, no, you definitely want, you know, if you
said silver maybe you really only want silver. But here the גמרא
gemara, seems to be okay with the idea that if he said
poor and it turns out that the guy is rich, that רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon would feel that we can accept רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon and say פשיטא, pishita, we don't talk about a שליח being
in the middle and מראה מקום. We say if it winds up
that the guy is a more, you know, qualified, you know, a
better marriage candidate,
he's rich rather than poor, that in that
case actually רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would say okay even though you
said על מנת al mnat that and the condition wasn't met, she's
definitely going to be happier with a rich guy rather than with
a poor guy. All right, so let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר עולא מחלוקת בשבח ממון.
Amar Ulla machloket beshvach mamon. Says Ulla,
the debate is when it's the guy wound up being, you know,
wealthier than than he said he was. He wound up being rich
rather than poor. By the way, what's the reason for the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma that they say it's no go? One you could
just be technical, I said on the condition that I am poor,
I'm not poor, so the condition wasn't met, end of story. Number
two is maybe they would say, you know, if we could be
certain that she would be okay with he'd be happier with him
being rich, you know, then maybe it would work, you know, but
maybe some people don't want to have to marry rich people, don't
want that type of a life with all that materialism or who
the heck knows. Okay, so that's not clear why the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma disagrees, the easiest explanation is the condition was the condition
and the condition wasn't met, and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon presumably assumes
even if the condition wasn't met, when you say על מנת al
mnat that, if we can assume the person would be happier with
the, you know, the alternative, then it's okay. And somehow that's better
than the wine and vinegar case where we're dealing with the object
to which which was created the marriage, you know, was given for
the marriage. So says עולא מחלוקת בשבח ממון. Ulla machloket beshvach mamon.
The debate is when it turns out that that was better in
terms of his finances. אבל בשבח יוחסין, aval b'shvach yichusin, but if
it turns out that the guy actually is has better יחוס yichus
than he said. He said on the condition that I'm a ישראל
Yisrael and he turns out to be a כהן. Kohen. On the
condition that I'm a ממזר mamzer and he turns out to be
not a ממזר. mamzer. דברי הכל אינה מקודשת. divrei hakol eina mekudeshet.
Everybody would agree it's not good. Why not?
מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? Because the woman could say מסאני דרב מכרעי
לא בעינא, masana d'rav mikara'i lo ba'ina, a shoe that's bigger than
my feet, לא בעינא, lo ba'ina, I don't want, I don't want
to walk in you know in a shoe that's too big for
my feet, you know, so I can't fill that person's shoes. So
I'm happier married to a guy that's of lowly status. A guy
that's such a high status, maybe I don't feel that I can
live up to that or that's going to create tension within the
marriage or whatever, you know, I never signed up to be the
wife of any big fancy כהן. Kohen. All right, so quite interesting.
Maybe that could also maybe be why the חכמים Chachamim might feel
the same way about rich and poor. The גמרא Gemara doesn't discuss
that. So now we're saying רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon even though the
condition isn't met, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says if it winds up
being better it works for her. But the גמרא Gemara, is saying
but better in terms of יוחסין yichusin is not necessarily better for
her and therefore רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon in that case would agree
it's not מקודשת. mekudeshet. Okay. תניא נמי הכי, tanya nami hachi, we
taught similarly, מודה רבי שמעון שאם הטעה לשבח יוחסין שאינה מקודשת. modeh
Rabbi Shimon she'im hit'ah l'shvach yichusin she'eina mekudeshet. It's exactly that. If
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would agree that if he deceived her and
the guy wound up being better from a status issue, a personal
status issue, that she is not מקודשת. mekudeshet. אמר רב אשי, amar
Rav Ashi, מתניתין נמי דייקא, matnitin nami daka, that's also comes emerges
from a close read of our משנה. Mishnah דקתני, de-katni, the משנה
Mishnah says, על מנת שאני כהן, al menat she'ani Kohen, because the
next משנה Mishnah coming up after this deals with the case, our
משנה Mishnah just dealt with poor and rich and there רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon said oh if it's better she's מקודשת. mekudeshet. The next
משנה Mishnah deals with כהן Kohen and לוי Levi and רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon does not voice his opposition. דקתני על מנת שאני כהן
ונמצא לוי לוי ונמצא כהן נתין ונמצא ממזר, de-katni al menat she'ani
Kohen v'nimtza Levi, Levi v'nimtza Kohen, Natin v'nimtza mamzer, if he says
I'm a נתין Natin which is a Gibeonite and finds that to
be a ממזר, mamzer, ממזר ונמצא נתין, mamzer v'nimtza Natin, ואינה מקודשת,
v'eina mekudeshet, and you know, אינה מקודשת. eina mekudeshet. ולא פליגי רבי
שמעון v'lo paligi Rabbi Shimon and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon doesn't disagree.
So it sounds like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is only voicing his
disagreement in poor and rich and not in a question of personal
status. מתקיף לה מר בר רב אשי, matkif lah Mar bar Rav
Ashi, מר בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi says that's not
a proof. אלא דקתני ela de-katni because the משנה Mishnah, goes on
to give another case, על מנת שיש לי בת או שפחה מגודלת,
al menat she'yesh li bat o shifcha megudelet, if he says on
the condition that I have a daughter or a female servant that
is you know older, not a kid, meaning and therefore able to
help out around the house, ואין לו v'ein lo and he doesn't
have, על מנת שאין לו ויש לו al menat she'ein lo v'yesh
lo or I don't have and he does have, also אינה מקודשת,
eina mekudeshet, the condition wasn't met. ורבי שמעון לא פליג, v'Rabbi Shimon
lo palig, and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon doesn't disagree. But ultimately that's
a case of being better off financially, having help around the house.
So you know you can't infer anything from the fact that רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon doesn't disagree in a later משנה Mishnah? that he
agrees, because this case about the maidservant or the daughter is certainly
one that he should disagree and it doesn't say it. אלא פליגי
ברישא, ela paligi b'reisha, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon voiced his opposition in
the beginning in our משנה Mishnah. that he says if it winds
up being better it's מקודשת. mekudeshet. והוא הדין לסיפא, v'hu ha-din l'seifa,
and that would apply to the cases we're going to discuss after
this, כהן, Kohen, לוי, Levi, I have a daughter or maidservant, I
don't have a daughter or maidservant, רבי שמעון would disagree with all
those and say that if it's better she's מקודשת. mekudeshet. הכי נמי
פליגי ברישא והוא הדין לסיפא, hachi nami paligi b'reisha v'hu ha-din l'seifa,
so here too we should assume that he could easily have disagreed
to the case of כהן Kohen and לוי. Levi. His silence doesn't
mean anything.
הכי השתא, hachi hashta, says the גמרא, Gemara how can you say
that? התם אידי ואידי שבח ממון, hatam idi v'idi shvach mamon, פליגי
ברישא והוא הדין לסיפא. paligi b'reisha v'hu ha-din l'seifa. Both of them
are the case about the maidservant is just another example of having
wealth. And therefore right, you could say that he doesn't have to
repeat his disagreement, he already said if a guy winds up being
wealthy it works. Okay. אבל הכא דשבח יוחסין הוא, aval hacha d'shvach
yichusin hu, the case about כהן Kohen and לוי Levi is a
fundamentally different category than the category of wealth. אי איתא דפליג ליתני.
ei ita d'palig litni. If he really disagreed he should have said
it. Okay, so yes, you can infer something from his silence. If
it's an exact application of the previous case of wealth, his silence
isn't meaning, why do I need to talk, I already said my
position. But when you're dealing with something like שבח יוחסין, shvach yichusin,
he should have disagreed and the fact that he didn't shows that
he agreed. Okay. איבעית אימא, iba'it eima, or if you want I
could say, הכי נמי שבח יוחסין, hachi nami shvach yichusin, the case
about having a maidservant or a daughter that's מגודלת megudelet is also
a case of similar to a case of personal status. That actually
he would
agree in this case, that in this case even having such a
person would not
the קידושין would not be good. How is this a case of
personal status and not a case of wealth?
So מי סברת מאי מגודלת... mi savrat mai megudelet... גדולה. Gedola. You
read the word מגדלת Migudelet meaning an adult daughter or maidservant. ממש.
Mamash. No, that's not true. מאי מגדלת? Mai Migudelet? What does מגדלת
Migudelet mean? גדלת, Gadalat, גדלת. Gadelet. Now what's a גדלת? Gadelet? So
you
know so רש"י Rashi says it means that she's like an important
person. תוספות Tosafot has a better answer. תוספות Tosafot says that it
means like it means actually a hairdresser. Okay now why is that
relevant? דאמרה Damrah cause דאמרה היא the wife could say לא ניחא
לי דשקלה מילי מינאי ואזלא וגניא קמי שבבותיה. Lo nicha li deshakeila
mili minai ve’azla ve’ganya kammai shivvuteh.
I don't want her to take my words and go talk amongst
the neighbors. So the way רש"י Rashi says it is if she's
an important person she'll feel comfortable talking among the neighbors, your daughter
or your maidservant. But or the way תוספות Tosafot says it, if
she's a hairdresser, you know that's what they do when you're making
doing the hair. You're talking, you're gossiping and so on. So in
those cases it's similar to the case of personal status. It's not
necessarily better that you have that woman who's a hairdresser coming into
her house. I could say actually that does not make me feel
comfortable. Okay because I'm afraid that she's going to spread gossip. Alright.
So according to this we're saying that in the case of the
next משנה Mishnah, of כהן Kohen and לוי Levi and so on,
even רבי שמעון would agree better isn't necessarily better for her. You
know, I don't want a person who has a higher status. I
don't want a person who's bringing these strange women into my house
and who knows going to go ahead and spread rumors. Okay. And
therefore רבי שמעון actually and that's why he does not disagree later
on. Okay.
Okay. Now תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Now that we're dealing with this
on the condition that I'm X, we're going to deal with different
conditions the person can say and what is considered to qualify for
that position, you know to say that that condition was met. All
right. So תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. על מנת שאני קרינא, Al menat
she'ani kraina, if a person says, you know, that I'm able to
read, I'm a reader, okay, כיון שקרא שלשה פסוקים בבית הכנסת הרי
זו מקודשת. Keivan shekara shelosha pesukim beveit haknesset harei zu mekudeshet.
If you're able to read three פסוקים, Pesukim, you got an עליה,
Aliyah, then you're considered literate. Okay. Yeah, I read books. So even
if you just read comic books, that counts. Okay. חס ושלום Chas
veshalom להבדיל Lehavdil בבית כנסת. Beveit Knesset. But the point being it
doesn't mean that you are some high level, minimum satisfying of the
condition counts. Okay. הרי זו מקודשת. Harei zu mekudeshet. רבי יהודה אומר
עד שיקרא ויתרגם. Rabbi Yehudah omer ad sheyikra veyitargem.
No,
a reader here and again reader has a context of like reader
of the תורה, Torah, I'm somebody who reads תורה. Torah. So once
I got an עליה Aliyah I'm able to read תורה. Torah. And
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah says no, reading תורה Torah includes the ability
to do תרגום, Targum, to read the תורה Torah and to do
the Aramaic translation.
You don't have to do a lot, but you have to be
able to read and to do תרגום. Targum. You know, so the
גמרא Gemara, says יתרגם מדעתיה? Yitargem mada’ateih? What? Like translate on your
own? Like just, you know, do your own freeform translation? והתניא רבי
יהודה אומר המתרגם פסוק כצורתו הרי זה בדאי. Vehatanya Rabbi Yehudah omer
hametargem pasuk ketsurato harei zeh badai. If you, you know, that we
have to do, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah says there's תרגום אונקלוס, Targum
Onkelos, there is the accepted traditional מסורה Masorah based תרגום Targum of
how to translate what these פסוקים Pesukim mean into Aramaic. And if
you go ahead and you want to do do it on your
own and you're going to be overly literal, even more literal than
אונקלוס, Onkelos, so then you are a liar because sometimes the literal
meaning of something is not the actual meaning. Okay. And תרגום אונקלוס
Targum Onkelos gives you the meaning as understood by the מסורה. Masorah.
והמוסיף עליו הרי זה מחרף ומגדף. Vehamossif alav harei zeh mecharef umegadef.
Or now you say, okay, well look, אונקלוס, Onkelos, you know, does
things that are not literal translation, so I'll also do a translation
and I'll go ahead and I'll add to what's on, you know,
I'll do my own freeform, you know, additions. Then that's then you
know you're a liar and you're a blasphemer, you're misrepresenting the תורה.
Torah. If you're overly literal or if you're overly loose, you're misrepresenting,
you have to go ahead and do it exactly as the תרגום
Targum does it.
So when רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah is talking about this condition being
met, how could he say if you're able if you do תרגום,
Targum, if it's you know, to it's seems like he's condoning freeform
translating, which we know he is against. So the גמרא Gemara
says אלא מאי תרגום תרגום דידן. Ela mai targum targum didan. No,
it doesn't mean that you're able to do it on your own,
it means that you're able to do the accepted תרגום דידן, Targum
Didan, our our Aramaic translation,
understood to be the תרגום אונקלוס. Targum Onkelos.
Okay, so if you said I'm able I'm a reader, a תורה
Torah reader, that means like, you know, like all you have to
do is read three פסוקים. Pesukim. Or read three פסוקים Pesukim with
the תרגום. Targum. והני מילי דאמר ליה קרינא, Ve’hanei milei de’amar lei
kraina, like I read the תורה. Torah. Okay. אבל אמר ליה קרא
אנא, Aval amar lei kara ana, meaning I read the תורה, Torah,
I read it every once in a blue moon I get an
עליה Aliyah as long as it's my בר מצוה פרשה. Bar Mitzvah
Parshah. But if you say like I'm a בעל קורא, Ba'al Korei,
I'm a reader with a capital R, קרא אנא עד דקרי אורייתא
נביאי וכתבי בדידקוקא. Kara ana ad dekari Oraita Nevi'ei u'Chtuvei bedidkuka. Then
it
that the condition is only met if you're able to read תנ"ך
Tanakh and you're able to read it with דקדוק, Dikduk, you're able
to read it with like with high precision. Okay. על מנת שאני
שונה, Al menat she'ani shoneh, if you say, I'm a learner, I,
you know, שונה Shoneh means like משנה, Mishnah. meaning it's not like
גמרא, Gemara's it's not like analysis, like it's knowing the the core
material of תורה שבעל פה. Torah Shebe’al Peh. So I learn. So
על מנת שאני שונה, Al menat she'ani shoneh, חזקיה אמר הלכות, Hezekiah
amar Halachot,
you have to like if you know the הלכות... Halachot... מסיני. MiSinai.
רבי יוחנן אמר תורה. Rabbi Yochanan amar Torah. If you know תורה.
Torah. Now that's a bit bizarre because שונה shona usually means תורה
שבעל פה. Torah She-be'al Peh. מיתיבי Meisivei איזו משנה? eizu Mishnah?
What constitutes משנה? Mishnah רבי מאיר אומר הלכות. Rabbi Meir omer halachos.
הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha l'Moshe MiSinai
constitutes משנה. Mishnah. Interesting. That's what רש"י Rashi says הלכות halachos means.
It could just mean like simple apodictic types of rulings, you know,
that make their way into the or incorporated in the משנה, the
תוספתא. Tosefta. Anyway, basic rulings is משנה. רבי יהודה אומר מדרש. Rabbi
Yehuda omer Midrash. So מדרש. Midrash.
Now what does מדרש Midrash mean? It doesn't mean מדרש Midrash like
when we talk about the מדרש Medrash says, which is, you know,
which is called מדרש אגדה, Midrash Aggadah, like the one that does
more on the narratives of the תורה. Torah. We mean מדרש הלכה,
Midrash Halacha, ספרא, Sifra, ספרי, Sifrei, מכילתא, Mechilta, the like the the
rabbinic legal interpretations of the פסוקים pesukim that are also like, you
know, very sort of simple, short, mishnaic type of stuff. The משנה
is the reorganizing around that and not linking it to the פסוקים,
pesukim, but, you know, extracting it from the פסוקים pesukim and organizing
it based on theme and topic and so on. Okay.
So the my so the גמרא says, you're right. מאי תורה מדרש
תורה. Mai Torah Midrash Torah. Okay, you're right, you're right, you're right.
When he said תורה, Torah, he meant the מדרשים Midrashim on the
תורה. Torah. So if you say I'm a learner, you know, I'm
a learner of תורה שבעל פה, Torah She-be'al Peh, you know, then
that means like you know basic הלכות halachos or you know basic
מדרשי הלכה. midreshei halacha. ואני מידי דאמר לה תנינא, Va'ani midi d'amar
lah tanina, I'm a learner, אבל אמר לה תנא אנא, Aval amar
lah tana ana, I'm a תנא, tana, which again is like a
title, not just I learn, but I'm a תנא. tana. תנא Tana
were the people that really made their job of memorizing all the
material. So what does that mean? עד דתני הלכתא ספרא ספרי ותוספתא.
Ad d'tani hilchata Sifra Sifrei v'Tosefta. You have to know everything, all
the הלכות, halachos, all the מדרשי הלכה, midreshei halacha, all the
תוספתא. Tosefta. You gotta know the whole thing. Okay, now על מנת
שאני תלמיד, Al menat she'ani talmid, if you say I'm a student,
and again תלמיד talmid as opposed to תנא tana or תנינא tanina
here means, you know,
like the גמרא, analysis, not just the memorizing of the material. What
constitutes satisfying that condition?
לאו כגון שמעון בן עזאי ושמעון בן זומא. Lo k'gon Shimon ben
Azzai v'Shimon ben Zoma. You don't say like שמעון בן עזאי Shimon
ben Azzai and שמעון בן זומא Shimon ben Zoma who were called
תלמידים talmidim because they never got סמיכה smicha even though they were
the biggest תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, you know, of their generation. אלא
כל ששואלים אותו בכל מקום דבר אחד בלימודו ואומר. Ela kol shesho'alin
oso bechol makom davar echad belimudo v'omer. Something that you can ask
him one thing from all the things he learned. That's the way
רש"י Rashi reads it. You could read it you can ask him
from anywhere he was supposed to have learned, you know, and he
has to be able to answer. But רש"י Rashi says much more
generous read and it sounds like this that this is the פשט.
pshat. You know, if if you're able to ask him from one
area that he's learned and he's able to give you a good
answer, that means that he's a תלמיד. talmid. ואומרו, v'omro, he's able
to explain it. ואפילו במסכת כלה, V'afilu beMasechet Kallah, even in מסכת
כלה, Masechet Kallah, which is a very easy area of
study. Okay, so he learns. על מנת שאני חכם, Al menat she'ani
chacham, but if he says on the condition that I am a
sage. By the way, תלמיד talmid and חכם. chacham. Right? It used
to be that the חכמים chachamim were the ones that had סמיכה
smicha and they were the sages. תלמיד חכם Talmid chacham was a
student of the חכם. chacham. So חכם chacham is obviously at a
higher level. So what constitutes a
חכם? chacham? לאו כחכמי יבנה, Lo k'chachmei Yavneh, like the sages of
יבנה, Yavneh, like רבי עקיבא וחבריו, Rabbi Akiva v'chaverav, רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva and his colleagues. אלא כל ששואלים אותו דבר חכמה בכל מקום
ואומר. Ela kol shesho'alin oso davar chochma bechol makom v'omer. As long
anything that you ask him a matter of analysis and חכמה, chochma,
right, and he's able to answer. רש"י, Rashi, by the way, says
it's not even in learning. If he says let's say he says
where's your חכמה? chochma? Well, in physics. Okay, well, you know, help
me understand this this physics issue. All right, so you know, this
quest this question I have about about biology or about math or
about art. Okay, so that's it. I said I'm a חכם. chacham.
I'm a חכם chacham in my own area. Okay. על
מנת שאני גבור, Al menat she'ani gibbor, on the condition that I'm
a valorous, לאו כאבנר בן נר, lo k'Avner ben Ner, or like,
you know, mighty powerful וכיואב בן צרויה, v'kiYoav ben Zeruiah, like these
major generals. אלא כל שחבריו מתייראין הימנו. Ela kol shechaverav misyair'in heimenu.
Anything that his, you know, friends are afraid of him. Like you
don't want to get into a fight with so-and-so, you know, מפני
גבורתו, mipnei gevurato, because afraid of him, right, because of you know
of his power, of his strength, of his physical strength. על מנת
שאני עשיר, Al menat she'ani ashir, on the condition I'm rich. Our
case in the משנה. לאו כרבי אלעזר בן חרסום וכרבי אלעזר בן
עזריה, Lo k'Rabbi Elazar ben Charsom v'k'Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah, who are
extremely wealthy people. It doesn't mean like, you know, Jeff Bezos or
whatever. So אלא כל שבני עירו מכבדים אותו מפני עשרו. ela kol
shebnei iro mechabdim oso mipnei oshro. Anybody that's considered rich in his
social context and people respect him because of his wealth, give him
honor because of his wealth. על מנת שאני צדיק, Al menat she'ani
tzaddik, on the condition that I'm righteous. אפילו רשע גמור מקודשת. Afilu
rasha gamur mekudeshet. Even if the guy was known to be a
complete wicked person, she's married. Why?
שמא הרהר תשובה בדעתו. Shema hirhir teshuvah beda'ato. Maybe at that moment,
you know, he decided to do תשובה. teshuvah. Now, this is actually
quite fascinating, because this is the first place where there's a שמא.
shema. So so the פוסקים poskim basically say she's ספק מקודשת. safek
mekudeshet. The other cases, we were saying what is a minimum satisfying
of the condition. This is שמא, shema, maybe. maybe not. So it's
only ספק מקודשת. safek mekudeshes. The other point is, רב סולובייצ'יק Rav
Soloveitchik discusses this גמרא in his על התשובה Al HaTeshuvah because normally
we talk about
תשובה teshuvah requiring וידוי פה, viduy peh, you have to verbally acknowledge
it, you have to do חרטה, charatah, you have to do קבלה
לעתיד, kabbalah l'atid, you have to be מרצה חבירו, m'ratzeh chaveiro, but
he says there's two aspects. There's תשובה teshuvah to forgive the sin,
which is that process that we were talking about, but he says
then there's the question of who are you, your personal transformation. And
some people could have a split second momentary, miraculous transformation in terms
of who they are as a human being and can go from
being a רשע rasha to a צדיק. tzaddik. Doesn't happen often, but
that's why he didn't say on the condition I did תשובה. teshuvah.
He said on the condition that I'm a צדיק, tzaddik, and who
knows, maybe all of a sudden he finds the right woman and
he's now has completely turned his life around. Okay. Okay. על מנת
שאני צדיק, Al mnat she'ani tzaddik,
if he says on the condition I'm a צדיק, tzaddik, אפילו רשע
גמור מקודשת, aphilu rasha gamur mekudeshes, even if he's a total רשע
rasha she's מקודשת, mekudeshes, again ספק מקודשת, safek mekudeshes, שמא הרהר תשובה
בדעתו. shema hirhir teshuvah b'da'ato.
I'm sorry, did I skip a line? על מנת שאני צדיק אפילו
רשע גמור. Al mnat she'ani tzaddik aphilu rasha gamur. I'm sorry, I
just did that. על מנת שאני רשע, Al mnat she'ani rasha, on
the condition that I'm a רשע, rasha, אפילו צדיק גמור מקודשת, aphilu
tzaddik gamur mekudeshes, even if he had been known to be a
צדיק גמור, tzaddik gamur, she's מקודשת, mekudeshes, שמא הרהר דבר עבודה זרה
בדעתו. shema hirhir devar avodah zarah b'da'ato. Maybe he had a thought
of being עובד עבודה זרה. oved avodah zarah. Somebody could be a
צדיק tzaddik their whole lives, אל תאמין בעצמך עד יום מותך, al
ta'amin b'atzmecha ad yom mosecha, and then have a complete transformation to
evil. All right, it's thrilling and terrifying at the same time. All
right, so that's what satisfies. Now, since we're talking about all these
things, rich and poor and wise and not wise and all that,
we're going to end with a little אגדתא. Agadta. All right. עשרה
קבין חכמה ירדו לעולם, Asarah kavin chochmah yardu l'olam,
ten measures of wisdom came down to the world, תשעה נטלה ארץ
ישראל, tishah natlah Eretz Yisrael, nine were taken by ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, the land of Israel, ואחד כל העולם כולו, v'echad kol ha'olam
kulo, and one the rest of the world. עשרה קבין יופי ירדו
לעולם, Asarah kavin yofi yardu l'olam, ten measures of beauty, תשעה נטלה
ירושלים, tishah natlah Yerushalayim, nine were taken by ירושלים, Yerushalayim, ואחד כל
העולם כולו, v'echad kol ha'olam kulo, one the rest of the world.
עשרה קבין עשירות ירדו לעולם, Asarah kavin ashirous yardu l'olam, ten measures
of wealth, תשעה נטלו רומיים קדמונים, tishah natlu Roma'im kadmonim, nine were
taken by the early Romans, ואחד כל העולם כולו, v'echad kol ha'olam
kulo, one the rest of the world. עשרה קבין עניות ירדו לעולם,
Asarah kavin aniyous yardu l'olam, ten measures of poverty, תשעה נטלה בבל,
tishah natlah Bavel, nine were taken by בבל, Babylonia, the תלמידי חכמים
talmidei chachamim in בבל Bavel were very poor, ואחד כל העולם כולו,
v'echad kol ha'olam kulo, one the rest of the world. עשרה קבין
גסות ירדו לעולם, Asarah kavin gasus yardu l'olam, of
ten measures of like haughtiness came down to the world, תשעה נטלה
עילם, tishah natlah Elam, nine were taken by עילם, Elam, ואחד כל
העולם כולו, v'echad kol ha'olam kulo, one the rest of the world
of the world. וגסות לבבל לא נחת? v'gasus l'Bavel lo nachas? The
Gemara says wait a minute, I thought haughtiness was a trait of
בבל. Bavel. והכתיב ואשא עיני ואראה, v'haksiv v'esa einai v'ereh, I lifted
up my eyes, this is Zechariah talking, and I saw והנה שתים
נשים יוצאות ורוח בכנפיהם, v'hinei shtayim nashim yotzos v'ruach b'canfeihem, two women
were going out and there was wind in their wings, ולהנה כנפיים
ככנפי החסידה, lahena cnafayim c'canfei hachasidah,
they had wings like the wings of the חסידה, hachasidah, a stork,
ותשאנה את האיפה, vatissana es ha'eifah, and
they lifted up the איפה, eifah, this measure, בין הארץ ובין השמים,
bein ha'aretz uvein hashamayim, between the heavens and the earth, ואומר אל
המלאך הדובר בי, va'omar el hamalach hadover bi, and I said to
the angel: אנה הם מוליכות את האיפה, anah heim molichos es ha'eifah,
where are they bringing this measure? ויאמר אלי לבנות לה בית בארץ
שנער, v'yomer elai livnos lah bayis b'eretz Shinar, to build a house
in the land of Shinar. ואמר רבי יוחנן, v'amar Rabbi Yochanan, זו
חנופה, zu chanufah, וגסות הרוח, v'gasus ha'ruach, this is flattery and haughtiness
שירדו לבבל, she'yardu l'Bavel, that went down to Bavel. That's where they
were bringing it. So you see the haughtiness is primarily in Bavel,
not in Elam. So the Gemara says: אין להכא נחית, in l'hacha
nacheis, yes, it went to Bavel, ואישתרבובי הוא דאישתרבוב להתם, v'ishtarvovei hu
d'ishtarvov l'hasam, and then it rolled and found its way to Elam.
It started in Bavel but it ended up in Elam. דייקא נמי
דקתני לבנות לה בית, dikna nami d'csani livnos lah bayis,
it also can be inferred it says to build for her house,
to build a house, but the house was never built. שמע מינה,
shma mina, that is a good proof. איני, ei ni, now is
this really true that Elam has haughtiness and not Bavel? והאמר מר,
v'ha'amar mar, סימן לגסות עניות, siman l'gasus aniyous,
that a sign for haughtiness is poverty, ועניות בבבל הוא דאיכא, v'aniyous
b'Bavel hu d'ika, and we know poverty is in Bavel like we
just said. So the Gemara says: no, מאי עניות? mai aniyous? עניות
דתורה. aniyous d'Torah. Aniyous means poverty of Torah. That if you're haughty,
then you do not, you're just okay with your learning, you don't
work hard to make sure you understand it, you don't become more,
you don't give yourself over to other people and make self-sacrifice, so
that's the problem. דכתיב, d'chsiv, אחות לנו קטנה ושדים אין לה, achous
lanu ktanah v'shadayim ein lah, we have a young sister and she
does not yet have breasts, ואמר רבי יוחנן, v'amar Rabbi Yochanan, זו
עילם, zu Elam, this refers to Elam, which is the place of
haughtiness which we said, שזכתה ללמוד ולא זכתה ללמד, she'zachsa lilmod v'lo
zachsa lelamed,
there were people there who learned the Torah, but they never merited
to produce teachers of Torah because they were too haughty to ever
get that level of knowledge to be able to really teach others.
עשרה קבין גבורה ירדו לעולם, asarah kavin gevurah yardu l'olam, ten measures
of strength went down to the world, תשעה נטלו פרסיים, tishah natlu
Parsim, nine for Persians, ואחד כל העולם כולו, v'echad kol ha'olam kulo,
the rest of the world, we're not bothering ending the sentence. עשרה
קבין כינים ירדו לעולם, asarah kavin kinim yardu l'olam, ten measures of
lice, תשעה נטלו מדי, tishah natlu Madai, nine were taken by the
Medes. עשרה קבין נגעים ירדו לעולם Asara kavin nega'im yardu la'olam ten
measures of leprosy or whatever, נגעים, nega'im, תשעה נטלו חזירים tisha natlu
chazirim nine were taken by the pigs. י' קבין זנות ירדו לעולם
yud kavin znut yardu la'olam ten measures of licentiousness, תשעה נטלה ערביא
tisha natla Arvaya nine of them were taken by Arabia. עשרה קבין
עזות
ירדו לעולם Asara kavin azut yardu la'olam of like brazenness, תשעה
נטלה מישן tisha natla Meshan nine were taken by Meshan.
עשרה קבין שיחה ירדו לעולם Asara kavin sicha yardu la'olam
ten measures of idle chatter, תשעה נטלו נשים tisha natlu nashim nine
were taken by women. Okay, so there's the גמרא's attitude about that.
עשרה קבין שכרות ירדו לעולם Asara kavin shikhrut yardu la'olam
ten measures of drunkenness, תשעה נטלו כושיים tisha natlu Kushiyim
nine were taken by Ethiopians. עשרה קבין שינה ירדו לעולם Asara kavin
shena yardu la'olam ten measures of sleep, תשעה נטלו עבדים tisha natlu
avadim
nine were taken by slaves, ואחד נטלו כולם כולו ve'echad natlu kulam
kulo and one the rest of the world, and we will end
with this.